welcome to the global waste a summit a
first-of-its-kind online journey into
collective consciousness and practice
for this event over 150 trailblazing
pioneers and we space experts from North
America and Europe have been invited to
share their latest insights and
reflections on the subject bringing our
best discernment inside these
conversations the many approaches of
each we space linear to come to life as
we explore pathways into the collective
development and transformation of our
lives and culture at this time we are
delighted to have you join us on this
journey
[Music]
you
hi welcome to this conversation we have
with us Daniel snackin Berger and I in
Baden invited Daniel today because I
find him to be really exquisite he goes
into a full flow of topics and things
that are really really important for the
civilizations that we want to bring that
we want to be sign and not only in terms
of the fury but also in terms of the
practice and the practice not only in
the enterpreneurship sand the thing that
he creates in manifesting the world but
in buttoning himself he has a in my
perspective a very pioneering spirit and
a very curious mind and a very sharp
intellect but very well grounded in his
heart so today we're gonna have this
conversation would they know about the
we spaces but we're going to enter into
one questions through one particular
part of the work that I'm interested in
in sharing with the integral people
which is nootropics and complex medicine
science will rephrase that but then
we'll be going and navigating into
different types of things that will open
up but all directed into sensing what is
that we need to do in this moment where
are the practical steps where are the
actions activities what is happening the
world that can inform us what what we
can do in this moment of transition what
we can do to develop higher ways and
better senses who we are together as
collective so high they know Efrain on
this happy to be here thank you
I'm delighted to have you here today so
as I mentioned I want to have like one
entry point question for us to start
with around nootropics
and around the the work that you do in
the neuro hacker collective a but first
perhaps the first question is can you
tell us what the tropics are so that
people just like can't understand sure
why it's important yeah yeah so the
tropics are chemicals that enhance some
aspect of cognitive function the kind of
formal best definition of no tropics is
any chemical that can enhance some
aspect of cognitive function like memory
or focus or herbal fluency or pattern
recognition beyond someone's normal
baseline without meaningful negative
side effects and so this is in Contra
distinction to brain nutrients which are
all the vitamins minerals amino acids
fatty acids that brain just naturally
needs your nervous system and whole
factory embodied cognition a whole
physiology needs to be able to process
information well those aren't gonna
really elevate capacity beyond baseline
they're just gonna bring you back to
baseline if there's deficiency because
those are really part of the
evolutionary environment right so brain
nutrients are foundational things and
then what we think of as smart drugs
which are usually pharmaceuticals that
are for a TD or sometimes narcolepsy or
sometimes neurodegenerative diseases
that can enhance some aspect of
cognitive function but usually it's
fairly narrow and usually it's with some
side effects so this is adderall
modafinil
vyvanse Ritalin you know those kinds of
psychostimulants psych meds and many
other things so you know tropics or this
kind of interesting category that's
trying to see if we can elevate aspects
of cognitive and then more widely also
psycho cognitive function from a neuro
physiological you know biochemistry
perspective and if we can do it without
negative side effects any even ideally
with lasting benefits so that's kind of
the field and why it's interesting
mm-hmm
yes for me it's really interesting I
started to do a research similar to dial
back in the late 90s before red wool or
those were getting companies and I
started to use like water or not and I
started to use like ginkgo biloba and
things like that and just like notice
what happened to me what happened to us
to my name or what happens
rest of my possibility to focus and that
was really interesting and I know that
you've been developing a product when
the product is out and I've been testing
that and I really really enjoy it I can
tell you many different experiences that
I had who with with while yet but that's
not the point for the conversation but
the partner that I want to enter into is
do these I understand that that by using
nootropics we can enhance our cognitive
function but have you used it or have
you experienced what does it create when
when a certain group of people do it
together the SID and hence the
collective capacity it's an interesting
question so when we think of chemistry
and we think of affecting neuro
chemistry in a way that's gonna affect
people's psyches they're gonna affect
them in our personally in terms of
positive experiences we usually think of
in pathogens right so we're talking
about on the very mild side so many
reasons that people come together and
drink alcohol together or use marijuana
together is because they get to access
some shared state of experience and
maybe one that decreases inhibitions or
decreases anxiety and allows for some
increased bandwidth of connectivity and
then deeper than that is things like
MDMA MDA other usually phenethylamine
some tripped means some other categories
of psychedelic but that are specifically
empathy increasing that are kind of
relationship increasing in terms of the
neuro chemistry they affect which is
almost exactly opposite to it usually
happens with the no tropic class of
chemicals so if we reference not know
tropics but smart drugs again most
people are taking smart drugs for pretty
individualistic purposes right they're
having a hard time focusing and they're
not accomplishing as much as they want
to they want to increase their creative
productive output when they're on kind
of single solo work and so
federal works for that you know it as a
dopamine agonist will increase focus and
will increase motivation now
unfortunately as a pretty strong
exogenous dopamine agonist it also means
that if you use that for a while it's
going to decrease your own endogenous
dopamine regulatory process which means
addiction and memories really not
primarily dopamine mediated its
acetylcholine and and you know many
other neurotransmitters glutamates
involved and other catecholamines are
involved so that the brain is a very
complex organ right and the brain
nervous system body mind environment
complex as a whole complex of complex
systems and when we're especially
dealing with not just human physiology
but we're dealing with kind of the
psychiatry or psycho neural interface
we're looking at the way that the upper
right quadrant affects the other left
right we could look at the other side of
the way mindfulness and phenomenological
in the upper left affect you know the
upper right but typically when we're
thinking of the psychiatry direction
we're looking at the effect of body on
mine this is a really tricky thing to do
from an epistemology point of view
because not only do we have to factor
complex systems and many different
complex systems got brain access and
methylation and genomics and head trauma
and so many things but we also have to
factor across the best technologic
categories right how do we assess
causation of something rising in
consciousness from something arising in
Physiology without reducing one quadrant
to the other so we causation isn't an
adequate way of thinking about it but so
there's a lot of reasons that the whole
field of psychiatry and
psychopharmacology are just profoundly
in how to quit to the scope of the
actual Sneed's of that space into the
ontology of how the space works but you
know because we're typically with
psychostimulants were that people are
taking or non-potable effects they're
going to be affecting a pretty narrow
bandwidth of things they're usually
actually things that decrease empathy
if you drive dopamine and then that's
going to turn into increased
norepinephrine and epinephrine you can
move into a more sympathetic less
parasympathetic place and so one of the
common experiences that people have when
they're on psychostimulants for
increased productivity is as they get
more frustrated when someone interrupts
them and they have to do task switching
they have less empathy and sometimes
even depersonalization or D realization
and so one of our main goals was can we
increase can we support increasing focus
and attention and concentration and
memory and pattern recognition and those
kinds of cognitive traits without
negatively affecting their psychosocial
and maybe even positively affecting it
so this was like one of our our big
goals and if you think about it as how
to affect both sides of the meaningful
dialectics at once more ability to
intensely focus and better task
switching those are very very different
tracks and so then we're not talking
about a brain that's more optimized for
one or the other or a psyche that's more
optimized for one of the other we're
talking about a more adaptive system
they can actually respond adaptively
environment needs know so we that was a
really interesting deep dive for us to
look at the chemistry and the neurology
that was associated with very different
types of cognitive and psychomotor
states and see how can we seek to
benefit the adaptive capacity of the
whole system the endogenous regulatory
capacity of the whole system and across
those kind of dialectic differences and
has it been in your experience like
stories of of success what have you been
observing in your big site you know in
your own experience of course well I
mean so with with this product that
we've got to bring to a lot of people
now qualia we have a pretty meaningful
amount of data that's come back to us
mm-hm and one of the things that a lot
of people have reported is increased
empathy increased vicarious experience
increased social intelligence social
awareness
and a lot of decrease of inner anxiety
inner critic that damages people's
social capacity right that has them so
caught in internal loop that they
actually have less capacity to actually
pay attention to other people rather
than project possible triggers on other
people and so even though that wasn't
what it was designed for it was a design
constraint we were hoping it would move
in the direction of it's been beautiful
to see that that's actually been the
experience of many people especially
factoring that usually the processes the
derived cognitive chemistry did the
opposite that's interesting yeah I use
it once for for going into a keynote and
that I did a presentation and I was so
happy that they first I was so exhausted
the day before and then that day I was
so on and then I felt so happy I was
really literally feeling a beautiful
connection with people and very aware as
you said like there's a very specific
form of presence that happens so I think
that there could be a lot of research
that can be done around what happens
when we intentionally go into the space
as individuals to create a specific way
space while empowering ourselves or
enhancing ourselves through the use of a
nootropic
so that that would be interesting and
speaking about pattern recognition but
in a collective I would like to
definitely see that pattern recognition
there's something fun that you said
which is you know when we look at the
pharmacology of it
pattern recognition is significantly
mediated by dopamine right so when we
get excessive dopamine we get
schizophrenia and see patterns that
aren't there and I mean that's
oversimplifying but drug-induced
methamphetamine induced schizophrenic
breaks are exactly that right starting
to perceive and recognize patterns that
aren't actually there because of over
pattern fitting from being over
dopaminergic and under dopaminergic
means not
amazing patterns that most people would
recognize so that's a cognitive thing
but dopamine is also a major aspect of
emotional function in terms of people's
motivational and kind of reward
circuitry processes and what's so
interesting is that all the chemicals
that mediate cognitive process also
affect emotional process and vice-versa
and so a clearer thinking mind and a
emotionally more well balanced person
from a physiologic point of view
correspond very much and it doesn't mean
there aren't certain cases where one can
you know have a certain set of clear
thinking while having existential
depression but for the most part those
seem to be simultaneously optimized
generally mmm-hmm there's also this
thing where again this is not a complete
story and whenever I'm speaking with in
abroad Ian's we have to make sure we're
not over assessing cut causation from
one quadrant to another but the the side
of cognitive behavioral therapy which is
true which is that we are not just
perceiving the world directly we're
perceiving the world making meaning of
it and then emotionally reacting to not
just the perceptions with the meaning
that's basically not thinking clearly
right fair to say that's actually not
perceiving the world exactly as it is
not assessing risk appropriately right
not assessing reward or meaning or
interpretation appropriately taking old
traumas and over weighting certain
things in terms of meaning that's being
added so there's a way in which just
thinking more clearly relieves a lot of
emotional drama and dynamics because you
are not making up stories that just
aren't actually true and that aren't
clear thinking yes the brain is like
more active and more impressive able to
go faster into identifying things that
might be detrimental or fears or
bothering or cognitive biases and just
like see that with with clarity and then
moving on rapidly there's this really
fun chemical that is in Phase two
clinical trials for major depressive
disorder by a company called neural stem
right now many people if they're
familiar with
Epic's we'll heard of its called NSI 189
and it is basically a neurogenic this
company neural stem started out doing
ALS work and they were actually
developing neural stem cells and
injecting them they were also going to
do spinal cord injuries and they started
looking for small molecules that could
actually increase the proliferation of
the neural stem cells and they found
about six that did and then an SI 189
was their best shot and so rather than
have to actually put the stem cells in
they can use the small molecule orally
and the body's own process of creating
you know of neurogenesis creating new
neurons and hippocampus then they can
move throughout anywhere in the nervous
system is just increased this is like
super interesting there's a lot of ways
that you can increase neurogenesis but
this is actually a drug that's pretty
far along and even those for ALS to
begin with and it was for then you know
starting to look at actually repairing
damaged nervous system either from
neurodegenerative disease or injury the
reason it's curing major depressive
disorder their hypothesis is that
they're actually seeing increased
hippocampal volume grey matter density
volume in the hippocampus with use and
seeing decreased depression they're
actually seeing the depression as an
inability to process the total amount of
emotional information within is coming
and that as they can actually process
the information better they can actually
find solutions and conclusions and not
be overwhelmed and you know left in
those those emotional places and there's
a number of other techniques and
processes that work through neurogenesis
that are finding this so this is very
interesting of like increased
information processing capacity not
being just a cognate thing but being
very related to emotion which then of
course relates to someone's capacity for
we space right but then it seems that
it's a capacity to perceive right
because what is how do we perceive that
emotional information so I said like 10
I tend to think is the heart right there
is like that we have like that capacity
to sense and to sense if it's someone
else when we're there in presence with
them what is happening in their space or
intuition or instinct but then we get
the inside
from the verbal communication of
whatever they're telling us and you can
see when somebody is tight or is open or
and then that also creates a certain
space of trust a satanist space of
feeling together in in resonance I would
say with one another
you said perception I'd say a way that
we think about often is sensory input
perception information processing of
that sensory input to make meaning out
of it and informed choices and then
choice actuator output and then being
able to perceive again the effect of our
actions and we have a closed loop that
really defines what is adaptive in any
complex adaptive system and in any kind
of animal any biologic system sentry
input is worthless by itself if we can't
actually make sense of it enact on it
right action capacity would be
meaningless if it couldn't be informed
by the right information necessary to
make it the right action so evolution is
actually selecting for this closed-loop
information cycle of information input
information processing sense making
meaning making actuator output and then
learning and that's what allows
development and so then we think about
that from a neurologic point of view
what is the what are the what's the
neurophysiology involved in all three of
those stages and how do we actually
increase the effectiveness of that
learning loop that information
processing mode so you would name what
are the levels of development that that
nootropics would work on what would with
those I mean it's obviously the
cognitive one but would they be also
like in the emotional one or would be
because I have heard many learning right
learning and a skill but I also seen
videos of people that are doing artistry
or not doing arts and are using it for
more flow so it's right-brain left-brain
aid so could you talk a little bit more
about that I think the word know tropics
is may be too narrow here right
that that word is usually to denote
cognitive function specifically but as
we've been talking about cognitive and
emotional are not that separate and and
athletic capacities that relate to
sensing and motor capacity faster the
acetylcholine that increases motor
capacity is the same a seagull calling
that's focused on memory consolidation
and so the idea that those different
lines of development are totally
different independent separately
developable pathways inside our
physiology is just not how it works
right it's much more integrated system
than that and so affecting any of those
things you're gonna have some effect on
all of them and that's why we really
think about how do we increase it but in
one way you can call them all
information processing different types
of information being processed in
different ways right and so how do we
increase the effective information
processing capacity of the entire system
across all the lines of development
thank you that made me think about
information processing in the collective
level and I know that part of what
you're doing this work is larger than
just medicine isn't why I would want to
track what was your intent what is your
true intent what lies behind this
innovation what do you truly want to
create in the world by launching this
initiative its product the reason I mean
this product is one of lots of products
that we've got in development both for
medical applications and wellness
enhancement applications and all of that
just scratching the surface of what kind
of the future of human wellbeing
optimization looks like but why that
whole field is interesting I mean one
unnecessary suffering sucks right and
our system of medicine and our system of
well-being science is good at a few
things and we've kind of tapped those
things out it's really good when the
causation is really obvious and that
usually means acute causation
and if the causation is not really
obvious because it's either delayed in
time or it's multifactorial or it has a
complex causal cascade then we call it
not immune disease and neurodegenerative
disease aging cancer and just really
they're all idiopathic we don't really
know so we just do symptomatic treatment
the underlying fiscal structure of
medicine is misaligned but doing good
medicine because if we're as a business
if we want to optimize the lifetime
value of a customer and a customer is a
patient then we're not really looking at
preventing illness and we're not really
looking at curing it quickly because if
I got to do a billion dollars to go
through phase three clinical trials and
then we cure someone very quickly how
can we ever make the money back right
we're not interested these is that don't
affect that many people in
symptom treatment is great all right
symptom treatment that causes side
effects that you need another drug
that's a cross seller and upsell like
from a business point of view that's
great so the financial structure is
basically broken the IP structure where
we can only look at synthetic molecules
that are patentable and then only during
their patent life and then we have to
pretend like we're innovating new better
stuff just because they ran out of
patent life like the IP structure is
broken and the epistemology which is
that we're trying to do complicated
system science on complex systems right
we're trying to pretend that you can
adjust one or two variables in a
radically complex system and understand
what its gonna do like causation doesn't
make sense that way in a complex system
we have to think of it more
dispositional II and with much more
complex dynamics of inner causation so
we're interested in just a completely
new version of medicine and not even I
mean obsoleting medicine of well-being
science and optimization at the
physiology level but then obviously
that's just the upper right and that's
obviously affected by the environments
that people are in and lower right by
their psyche in the upper left right so
then this now we get into how does the
individual affect the collective and how
are they affected by the collective and
how do we work on those things together
so if we make better if we make an
environment that has less toxicity in it
then we're not dealing with diseases
that are
toxicological origin right the
individual the better systems of
agriculture better systems of education
media but the better economic system
that doesn't create stress economic
systems governance system sense making
systems now how can we affect
individuals today so that they influence
the collective in the right direction
both directions are true right the
Republican Democrat historic debates the
libertarian Marxist debates have been
around which of those directions were
more important and they are reciprocal
and so why we were real interested in
the kind of individual optimization side
is obviously human quality of life is
intrinsically meaningful period and it's
just intrinsically meaningful it's
actually meaning reifies in subjective
experience and the next step is that
we're not just interested in humans
having increased quality of life but
also increase capacity to act
meaningfully in ways that affect the
quality of life of everyone else right
not just human but all all things and so
it happens to be that what really
increases human capacity and what
increases their quality of life is the
same thing this is again optimizing
across a dialectic and so when we were
looking at existential crisis right
existential threats who are looking at
catastrophic risks of all kind and
environmental humanitarian social
economic dynamics when we're looking at
the way that they're all contributed to
by human action then the question
becomes well what are what are all the
influences of human action and how can
we work with those to predispose
fundamentally more Omni considerate
human action and of course there are
things that influence human behavior in
all objects and you know thinking about
the way the upper-left influences human
behavior is pretty clear right
psychological trauma when you're a kid
you need psychotherapy you need better
education you need a better definition
of success and your kind of individual
mimetic structure and the way the
lower-left right though
that macroeconomics affects human
behavior in terms of what do we actually
incent people to do we make we have an
economic system where the whales worth a
million dollars dead as well me but
nothing alive we're actually affecting
human behavior in a pretty clear way
through incentives right through
cultures were all status things through
language right patterns of reception
affected by language that affect
behavior so all of the quadrants lower
right environmental psychologies effect
on human behaviors radical right the
upper right human physiology affects you
in behavior not just meaning like mostly
when people start thinking about this
they start thinking about eugenics in a
hurry and what genes are fundamentally
better and worse and this this is a
really not adequate understanding when
someone's hormones are out of balance
when their neurotransmitters are out of
balance when their gut is in dysbiosis
they feel very differently and they
behave differently they have different
behavioral dispositions and different
capacities everyone's had a hangover
where like joy is just not accessible
it's not even an accessible thing and
it's pretty hard not to have negative
reactivity and other people have had
states where it's almost hard to be
negatively reactive based on physiologic
state and so we started looking at the
the neuro chemistry and the neuro
structure of psychopathy versus the
neuro chemistry and neural structure of
people with very high empathy and the
neuro chemistry and neuro structure of
impulse control disorders and of
aggressive patterns and recognizing how
much of human behaviors actually
influenced by physiology and what we can
do with both better agriculture systems
and better medicine systems better
activity systems I mean everything the
the paint in these walls is producing
VOCs that are neurotoxic there's like
fundamentally to really have optimally
healthy people requires rebuilding
civilization from scratch with that in
mind right we can start now to take
people who are interested and radically
increase their quality of life and
capacity so then they can start to
affect all the rest of what needs to
happen more and we can get virtuous
cycles
Wow
okay that's that's an entry point to the
integral civilizations design work that
you've been doing and so what is in your
perspective the things that people in
their ordinary people are listening to
us need to be looking into like these
steps that people can be more aware in
their lives so that we move together
into a pattern of well-being
hmm well it's a tricky question because
I don't know who's listening and what
capacities they have and what interests
and availabilities and etc so I would I
would generally talk about that and the
more personalized and hopefully relevant
way most of the times we think about
actions we can all do in our own life to
make things better at a global level we
think about pretty trivial and I don't
mean to say these things aren't
important but trivial relative to the
scope and urgency of the issues and
complexity we think about basically
consuming less stuff and organic
consuming better stuff or less stuff
right now which our focus is being less
bad where we are net negative we're
basically liabilities on nature's
balance sheet right rather than assets
on nature's balance sheet if you want to
look at the code amount of biodiversity
or the health and complexity of the
biosphere as a whole and we're looking
at can we slow how bad we are like it's
just a totally wrong way of thinking
about it I mean it's a fine starting
point to think about but really we
actually have to build a new human
civilization that is fundamentally on
the asset side of nature's balance sheet
that is net positive to everything
that's meaningful and that doesn't look
like a retrofit of this civilization at
all it looks like fundamental ground
redesign work I mean there now I don't
know how deep will go and how familiar
people are but there-there is no system
there's no version of capitalism it is
adequate as a system of macroeconomics
in the presence of exponential
technology and in the presence of answer
complexity and the fragility of the
biosphere at this point and etc that
doesn't lead to catastrophic giving
phones there's no version of
representative democracy within
nationalist governments that doesn't
lead to catastrophic problems so the
kind of shift that we need is axiom
level and I'm not gonna propose Marxism
or socialism or any other thing that
hasn't worked I'm gonna propose things
that are reverse engineered from design
constraints of what's actually necessary
and sufficient they're fundamentally
different than any kinds of systems
proposed so far but have learned from
them and learn a lot from how nature and
complement systems work so yeah if I if
I was to be saying in general what can
people do to be helpful to that I would
say be aware that civilization as we
know it is self terminating stop trying
to win at a self terminating game going
I know what start really earnestly
exploring what alternatives that might
be viable look like and how you can
contribute your life energy to them
mm-hmm so yeah let me do that I have to
agree with you in in regards to how
we're facing in these collapse in all
levels and the complexity is way too
fast for anyone to really know exactly
how so the amount of number of paths
possible it's overwhelming it's really
really overwhelming
so yeah why have you found in your
research that gives a hope for the
future what is that you found in your
research that it would say have you find
these places where you say we would find
these then
we could reverse into an infinite game
we can actually do this can we actually
do this yeah you know speaking to an
inner audience there are things that are
very helpful in each quadrant and then
across all the quadrants that are
already plausible and lower right we
need to stop building complicated
technology complicated built worlds and
start actually building emergent complex
worlds that are extensions of the design
principles and complexity of the natural
world and that are commensurate with it
and this means that you stop building
individual pieces of tech and you build
whole tech ecosystems right that are
regenerative closed-loop post growth
upcycling techy ecosystems and this
means entire materials economies where
you have a closed-loop on the atoms
right the atoms are actually you're not
needing new atom acquisition from mining
or virgin resource acquisition and
you're not turning any of the atoms into
wastes your fundamental circle our
economy yeah
circular closed-loop economy and that
where the same stuff gets to keep being
better in better forms within a fixed
number of atoms a post growth system so
basically steady-state system with a
we're looking at steady-state
populations that are aligned with the
carrying capacity of the planet and
they're up cycling because pattern
information continues to evolve and we
continue to impound new photons so we
have to think of atoms photons energy
and pattern as three totally different
non fungible things in the future of
economics we're going to be dealing with
a finite number of atoms we're gonna be
dealing with a much larger and less
bounded amount of energy and an almost
unbounded amount of information and so
those are those are non fungible with
each other so you can't relate them all
to a currency and trade them it doesn't
make any sense because I'm not
tradeable so so building the right kinds
of infrastructure that are actually
resilient complex closed-loop up cycling
infrastructure that's a very hopeful and
exciting thing is possible right in the
lower-left we can think about building
new systems of sense-making intelligence
right new systems of governance choice
making new systems of meaning making
collective meaning making you know
culture I talked about economics
actually new systems of basically
resource allocation and human
influencing patterns of human behavior
which are the two things that economics
really deeply does as we are moving to a
world where most of the shitty jobs can
be automated
one of the major axioms of why
capitalism mattered was how do we get
people to be the shitty jobs they're
like it's fun to lay roads for a day for
a couple days and learn how to do it but
nobody wants to spend their whole you
know multiple decades doing that 40 plus
hours a week but society needs it done
and so if the jobs need the people to
get done then we got to make it to where
the people need the jobs otherwise you
know if you do a Marxist thing we spread
the resources between everybody then
nobody wants to do the shitty jobs in
the state has to force when we call it
imperialism and so we don't like Marxism
so we like it when the market which is
if you don't do the shitty jobs you just
starve right but that's free and then we
say but you can educate yourself and get
a better job but that's statistically I
mean it's theoretically possible but
statistically very hard when those who
are born into more have more resources
to create more resources with those were
born into less have less she get these
ever widening gaps etc so but when you
can start to automate and you know we're
looking at automation of most of the
jobs over the next not not too many
years I'm not only you know all kinds of
jobs not only the automated very shitty
jobs were also high level right like
diagnosis medical anything that you can
write a procedure for
you can if you can write a procedure for
it you can make a machine to a better
than us if you can write a procedure for
it it's not that fun for creative beings
to spend must at much of their life
doing yeah and so you would have to
extrinsic Lee and sent them to do it
because infants are consented wants to
do things that are either connection or
creativity based yes and so what happens
is either we try and stick with
capitalism and have the most grotesque
inequality come with technological
unemployment or we say well wait the
whole reason major part of the
reason to the capitalism I'm using one
axiom there's obviously twenty others
but we can go through all of them is
well now that we the people that jobs
don't need the people anymore we can
also create a Commonwealth economics
where the people don't need the jobs and
we move from an economics of extrinsic
motive to a system of intrinsic motives
or than education is really about
facilitating the unique intrinsic
motives of everyone so we actually have
the ability to build a new macro economy
where the incentive of every agent and
the well-being of every other agent and
of the Commons are perfectly aligned
with no gap that gap is the basis for
externality and we've had externality
for forever but with exponential tech
most people don't really understand what
exponential curves do it it means that
our intuition and best practices of the
past get obsolete faster right our
externalities have already brought the
biodiversity of the planet radically
down a very short period of time post
industrialization but with exponential
tech in this part of the curve any
externality becomes catastrophic fairly
quickly and so in the presence of
exponential tech this the radically
increased capacity of individuals to
affect reality we have to affect reality
in if they have we have to have our
choice making increase as exponentially
as our impact of our choices do and so
the movement into exponential Omni
consideration right exponential good
choice making but we actually do have
the ability to make a macroeconomic
system based on that
where the all systems of systemic
incentive have no externality I mean
they're perfectly aligned with
well-being now it would take a while to
get into it but we actually have
architectures for how to do that so I'm
giving a few examples but I want to let
you so you ask what is hopeful
what's hopeful is that all the things
that suck are changeable mmm-hmm and
that there actually are adequate
architectures for what is necessary and
sufficient not just for survival but for
entering a fundamentally new phase of
civilization is actually worthy of that
term whether we do it or not as a
question mark but the possibilities of
all
yeah the possibility he's always asked
for nerd litter says he's like chased
crisis is a terrible opportunity to
waste so this is the moment and you've
spoken a lot about many economic systems
sense-making and then in the run I will
want to go a little deeper in the realm
of the lower left quadrant in the type
of the terms of the week so to get it
round into the part of how we create
those higher weeks right why does it
matter for people to right now get
together and get a better sense of each
other and connect on not only mentally
and cognitively but also in terms of
resonance and and an energy because yes
we want to be sign according to living
systems and according to nature and and
we are we are nature and as part of
nature in its evolution we also have the
Sphinx school identity and these things
called ego and these things called
shadow and these things called cognitive
biases that 3-stone neces don't have and
so what what would it be that part of of
what the weave of the other people can
do now and what is to get activated
together so that that we can inform each
other because you know in the way I see
it if jobs that are chilly are automated
release and go ahead with it do it all
machines thank you I think that human
beings that have the space for
innovation have the space for philosophy
have its space for culture have a space
for creativity and for other things that
we don't know
you know rounds that have been
unexplored because we don't have we
haven't had that time we but we need new
ways of making meaning together many
people make meaning because they have a
job even if it's a bad job that they
don't necessarily like they learn how to
make mini base upon that little realm
inquisitor increase they can act be
active so the integral people that are
exploring the way spaces I find that
that I would like to see that part of
that research or part of that reflects
an outcome that is more mainstream that
tells people how to connect when when
you're not necessarily in in alignment
in the levels of IDs or in the level of
values but you're in alignment with
other parts of yourself that's why I was
interested in seeing what are the the
ways in which we can create higher
states of consciousness or does that
make sense
great ok so we can see the world in a
phase of increasing radicalization
currently in many parts of the world
many parts of the industrialized world
and the the political philosophy around
this has been kind of the Machiavellian
enemy hypothesis which is the only way
to get people of very different
dispositions together as if there's a
larger enemy where they have to band
together otherwise they'll keep going
tribal until they get down to the Dunbar
number and that has been mostly true
right and so when you look at the
kind of very bizarre version of
postmodernism control left that is
really driving the cohesion of a bunch
of different groups into what's now
called the alt-right and the white
nationalist and etc movements with it
and you look at how far apart those are
from each other how the do you
bring that together right and how the
does that not become civil war and
how does civil war in the United States
not become world war well if the only
way to bring it together is to have an
external enemy we've been in more for
decades now right if is to have an
external enemy big enough that the right
and left our friends in relationships a
external enemy that's also a world war
yes all right so these strategies just
don't look good at all and so one of the
things is that the first even people who
understand military strategy military
history I think underestimates both
anthro complexity the complexity and the
unpredictability of 7 billion people and
how many non-state actors have so much
power and etc and I think they
underestimate what exponential tech
really means in terms of making that
anything applicable in the past is it is
like well now so to kind of get into
that you know we saw a couple weeks ago
now I don't know when this airs maybe
it'll be months ago a drone drop a
thermite bomb in the in the Ukraine on a
munitions factory and it created a you
know a multibillion-dollar level of
damage from one little drone you know a
near nuclear level of damage and we
don't know who did it but it's easy to
do and that was not even a swarm of
drones in building a swarm of drones
with AI swarming algorithms from github
that you can build in your own garage
and web like we have exponential tech
capability where non-state actors were
little bitty actors that we can't even
know if we're doing anything have
catastrophic capability
that's a big and it's in Greece
Christmas cards just became $1,000 a
year ago right and think about what that
means think about what the increasing AI
and nanotech capacities mean right and
so the first existential technology we
had detect where we could actually
everything that was the bomb but the
bomb was such a expensive difficult
thing to build the US was the only one
who had and then US and Russia two
superpowers they could be locked in me
to assure destruction with their Intel
systems locked on each other nobody
could use it we lived in a cold war as a
method safety yeah but as soon as we
have so many nuclear powers and you have
powers that are as significant as
nuclear that you don't even know where
they are they're radically multipolar
right how the did how do we make it
through that so one you know when we
define what we're interested in working
on one of the things we define is a
civilization that is resilient and anti
fragile in the presence of extra Kalidas
tributed exponential tech right how do
how do we have resilience and anti
fragility in the presence of that well
most answers to that go Orwellian in a
hurry Vic we deceive ourselves and know
who's doing what and be able to shut it
down because we can't let it happen
right well that's already a film state
because that level of disco hearin
stress perspective leads to failed
failed state for other reasons in
dystopian so the only answer we have to
make it through our power curve involves
we space involved a radical upregulation
of people knowing each other knowing
when someone is off no one being that
off because they feel so isolated and
disenfranchised and existential angst
'full hmm right and that being
structurally built in a way where it is
ubiquitous we actually have no way
making it through that doesn't include
that at the center now let me say it
another way because I think it is
valuable to think of it this way you
mentioned moving from finite to infinite
games and if there's anyone who hasn't
read that book it's a classic finding
infinite games to come into I'm gonna
speak to it in a even more popular and
simple way which is all finite games are
win-lose games we're actually coming to
an end of when lose game theory at a
social level and this is actually a key
way of thinking about we space on a
sports team we create a sense of we with
our team and we'll have a lot of
coherence with each other to be to beat
the other ones and we have a bay with
them right so we get to do in-group
out-group mentality now that's a
training - for kids to be good at that
psychology for when it's time for war
and you know whatever else frame go back
to tribes event the time of tribes would
create coherence with each other to be
able to be competitive with another
tribe if need be now if there's low
population relative to lots of resources
we're all cool with each other if the
population gets high relative to not
that many resources we start raising
that kill and the other people is a
viable strategy and trying to help
compete them for the scarce resources
also and then strategy so those are two
methods of competing now compete them
for scarce resources and directly
militarily attacks now throughout all of
history two things have been true one
this strategy worked
you actually could kill the other people
get the river front and life is better
for you and your people and two if
anyone else played win-lose games you
had two or lose by default
if you didn't create a military and
anyone else has realized this killing
other people thing works didn't you just
die by default and so militaristic
win-lose games have been necessary and
then a couple tribes joined together to
be able to fight the bigger tribe they
couldn't fight and so then you get more
tribes banding together so now we get
villages and kingdoms and nation-states
and global economic trading bloc's
and the tools of commerce increase we
get fiat currencies fractional reserve
banking etc to increase our power our
tools of extraction of resource from the
environment and our military tools
increase this is just upping the ante on
win-lose games right until we have the
biggest players we can possibly
have with the biggest tech we can have
in both our ability to compete for
scarce resource and to direct attack
each other when needed
but you get to a place about now where
you have so much power that you can no
longer win that winning requires
destroying the playing field equals
losing and if we try to out-compete each
other for the scarce resource we just
ruin the biospheres capacity to support
us and we get then massive migrations of
humans causing Wars and everything else
and if we try and actually beat each
other with our military technologies
everybody does because we have way too
much military technology that's never
been true before war always worked out
competing them for resource always
worked it will never work again and so
we're at a place where win lose game
theory which equals strategy the word
strategy means win lose game theory how
to be effective in the menues game
that's like all military strategy man
business strategy derived from military
strategy that's gone because that
becomes Omni lose-lose so either we
figure out Omni win-win which means how
do we meet needs while meeting the needs
of everyone else involved and the
biosphere without externalizing harm at
all either we figure that out or our
species has finished its experiment so
what does that mean from a we space as
it means there is no other so we
actually have to get off in-group
out-group mentality there is no answer
to making it through our technological
capacity an existential risk without
getting past in-group out-group
mentality and having it all be in-group
so by developing the capacity
be together capacity to trust each other
capacity to in these moments where we
don't know where things are going it's
probably a good idea for people to be
starting deeper relationships with one
another for all the people who thought
Hillary was gonna win before the
election to understand how badly broken
their sense-making systems were that the
world that they thought they lived in
the world they actually live in are not
the same they don't map and that if your
sense making is not good you are not
adaptive at all you will lose all
adaptive capacity and we put our sense
making outside in the wrong places
in your Facebook feed and then your you
know whatever fund that you listen to
that are not actually informed either
and so the thing to get is if you're if
you are bending it if you're doing
in-group out-group stuff right and
whether it's the lean green meemers or
you're out group or it's alright as
you're out group your capacity to
actually improve things is pretty much
none at all
you
okay I'm gonna take a deep breath with
all that still feel the connection to
and I don't want to see it's a hope
because who fields a bit passive but to
that place of opportunity within
ourselves to come into these times and
leave our own youto our own not I would
say it was like Hollywood shows us all
this dystopia sand they seem to be fun
and when will you talk about your utopia
said we would have utopic movies
probably know where it would go right
you know so but if we can hold that
together that we can go into that curve
that we can lift each other up we can
elite wouldn't one another through the
creation of community through the
creation of relationship with people
that we don't necessarily want to relate
with or they're not the same as us or
they don't sure it's exile use but it
seems that is the time for us to get
over our edges with one another
and enter and try to do those with
spaces with the people that are not
necessarily similar to us this is the
key part I want people to give it's so
easy for us to reach a point of what
seems like fundamental disagreement and
then just disconnect I'm not gonna hang
out with this person for I'm not gonna
hang out this group of people or
them let's start a war or let's just
ignore them right let's just get those
people because they are effectively bad
to us doesn't work anymore we actually
can't win those wars because there's a
lot of people that think that whatever
that thing is and they have exponential
techtube and as soon as you realize that
we share the planet and we actually
can't get the other groups off then you
say I've got to actually figure out
what is it that is meaningful to them
and the day value and where can we build
bridges and the whole just I
I'm going to not interact with them and
them that just doesn't work and so
then you start asking more questions and
you open up your willingness and
capacity for understanding understanding
bridge building what so what is that
understanding of bridge building and
where are transition technologies that
you see already happening that people
can start to be aware of we're
prototyping a very interesting process
of sense making right now that involves
human sensors and I'll tell you one step
in it
partner partner mind forest land
redevelop this Partners got a really
beautiful insight so group of people
come together for governance for choice
making you can't do choice making before
you've done since making because you
don't know what the to do right you
and so one of the one thing we can say
is that if your governance system
involves voting it's already broken
because voting means that some things
that are valuable are going to be
benefited at the cost of other things
that are valuable we're gonna see who
values which ones more again in an
exponential curve world that just
doesn't work whenever things are being
harmed and they're becoming catastrophic
and you polarized the people who are
associated with the different values so
typically when we have a choice to make
it's like do we bow yes or no on this
proposition both sides suck because it
was a welfare it was a ill firm
proposition right so we get the we get
the economics but we destroy the
environment or we keep the environment
destroy the economy we actually need to
do a better job of understanding
everything that is meaningful regarding
this decision and all that's
interconnected first and take all those
as design constraints to an integrated
design process and so there's a sense
making the proceeds a choice making and
so part of how this process works is
group of people come together to do the
sense-making regarding an issue and
let's say the the issue is do we build
this bridge or not right or the issue is
what is a adequate governance system or
whatever so we start with a whole bunch
of questions right we have a whole bunch
of questions that are relevant to answer
this and and so the question might be
[Music]
let's say we're asking say we were
leading one on governance itself what do
we think of liquid democracy what do we
think of voting currencies what do we
think of non voting systems would we
what are the strengths and weaknesses of
dynamic governance or socio cracy where
you know whatever right you have a whole
bunch of things what about when is
meritocracy useful versus consensus so
then you have all these questions and
then people that are interested in those
questions break off into small groups
and they ask a few questions related to
that question one question is in order
to answer this question what additional
questions would we have to ask and
there's a process that is facilitated
well I guess in order to to you know
answer that question regarding say is a
voting currency a good system we'd have
to say well what what are the effects of
voting systems at all and how do we
define what kind of choice should be
benefited or are there different kinds
of choices that need different kinds of
governance systems and how do we relate
it to sense making so you start to find
there's a whole taxonomy of questions
underneath it that you just either
didn't pay attention to or you assumed
the answers to now everyone in the group
will have different insights as to what
questions what is the level of
consciousness and and training of the
people that are involved in order to be
able to engage in it how much civic
engagement training is necessary
whatever at all these questions and then
you also ask what underlying assumptions
are there and what is ultimately
meaningful that this is trying to
address now as you go around in a
structured process no one is actually
giving answers anywhere and no one is
proposing strategies they're saying this
question has these other questions
connected and then everyone gets be like
oh I wouldn't have even thought of
that question oh that's interesting
and because we're not jumping straight
to vote you don't get pissed off that I
want this thing that
feels like it's gonna take away from
your thing you get to say well yeah I
guess spotted owls are interesting too
right if there's a way of doing it that
doesn't damage my kid getting a job and
oh I guess I do have that assumption
underneath it and I guess this is
actually what's meaningful to me well
should the things that they said are
meaningful to them or meaningful to me
too so in the process not only does a
huge amount of information get surfaced
that then can go into a choice making
process they can lead to better choices
but all of the people understood each
other better and they actually
understood how to do an aspect of we
space better which is I understood how
to notice their own assumptions how to
notice what's actually meaningful to
them that is driving where their motion
is and how to ask more questions and
they became more it you know educated
about the topic and they after they do
this a bunch of times they start to take
for granted that there's a huge amount
of stuff they don't know about
everything they're passionate about and
they start to take for granted that
other people that have perspectives that
they thought they would have differed
with actually have meaningful things to
share that they didn't know via going
through that process so of course we end
up surfacing some sense-making in the
form of documents but we surface
sense-making in the form of all of the
people being better sense makers are you
actually training a kind of civic
engagement so when you ask what are some
tools or processes to be able to help
people actually connect and relate
better that's this one example I just
said okay so it's like by is trying to
develop selves breaking by developing
more sense making in the forms of
questions and then starts by asking
those questions and then helping people
to actually relate first to that instead
of trying to get into the answers I am
by doing that they create some empathic
connection because there's nothing to
oppose there are just questions
we're just surfacing that which we don't
know and then but then how do you go
from that because you know in the in our
when we do collective intelligence
processes we can have all these huge
amounts of data and this huge amount of
harvesting but I tend to think about it
like in form of a spiral right so we go
from the outer to the
inside and the inside is where we want
to find that answer to our question and
sometimes what happens is that people
are not able to then see the whole of
what is emerging in a way that makes
sense we can develop a huge map but that
doesn't mean people will be able to make
sense of that map so what is the process
in which you going through that kind of
huge amount of data and questions into
the actual more focused way of sense
making from that to this seeing what
you're actually wanna see yeah so the
second simplicity on the other side of
the complexity is actually an integrated
design itu surface all of this
complexity of questions and of things
that are meaningful and things that
matter right that's ultimately gonna
create a series of design constraints
right for sure and then the design
constraints are going to be the
beginning of a integrated design process
and the simplicity the choice that's
made is actually a design that meets all
the design constraints and so the future
of governance and economics actually
here is around integrated design this is
a really different thing it's not
optimization and it's not game theory so
when we think of optimization right we
say okay we have a bit of a system and
there's a whole bunch of different needs
that need met and I've got you know I
have my government budget my state
budget or my federal budget or whatever
it is and I've got military needs and
healthcare needs and all these things
where I have a company and I have our
total amount of money and I've got
marketing needs and HR needs and product
needs and R&D needs but now I'm going to
allocate the resources the same scare
seemingly competitive resources to each
of the different areas in light of what
they'll be able to do in that area how
it all comes together that will create
the best whole I'm thinking about the
whole from an optimization point of view
so we look for global Optimum's when we
look for Nash equilibriums and things
like that that's kind of how we've done
it that will definitely not work moving
forward
and for a few reasons
one is when we think about optimization
we are assuming that we're dealing with
theory of trade-offs that the same
resource going to this area is taking
away from this area and coming here is
taking away from this one which when you
actually get into integrated design
where you look at the synergy
possibility of how can these things be
mutually beneficial it's not about how
much resource goes here and here it's
about what is a design that works for
both of these things together better
than the inside of either of them on
their own would have and so as long as
we have underlying theory of trade-offs
we will have people that are associating
with whatever value metric they care
about particularly and will continue to
radicalize and polarize people just
through the underlying theory of
trade-offs though the key is not how do
we top-down allocate or how do we
bottom-up have a bunch of agents that
try to find Nash equilibriums it's how
does everyone surface what is ultimately
meaningful to them and we take all these
sources of meaningfulness as design
constraints and then we go into a
collaborative design process with the
people who have the appropriate
capabilities for that particular kind of
thing and a design that meets all the
design constraints can move forward with
consent Wow so that's how would you
describe integrated design when we go
from the sense making into identifying
the design constraints and then we find
the most simple elegant way of meaning
those design constraints and what about
paradox what about those design
constraints that come from paradoxical
sets of needs some people may think they
need this and another people think they
need it and there's like there's
opposition on that so always false
dichotomy and the key there is to move
from false dichotomy into dialectic and
then synthesis on the dialectic and so
people's strategies for how to meet a
need will be fundamentally and
reconcilable but the actual need
will not be fundamentally unreconciled
so we have to be able to tease apart the
strategy for how to meet the need in the
actual need and so this is again where
we get into assumptions right there's an
assumption that this particular strategy
is the way to meet that need and there
is a meaningful - right what is actually
meaningful here well ok so my strategy
to meet the need for freedom is lays a
fair free market capitalism
well no but my strategy for the way of
meeting my need for tending to though
tending to the disabled and those who
are in you know harder off positions and
tending to the Commons as Marxism well
no let's let go of the strategies and
say what I care about is individual
freedom and sovereignty and the creative
capacity of the individual what I care
about is the Commons and the
Commonwealth and those who are not in
positions to be able to fully take care
of themselves sovereignly being taken
care of great those are not in
fundamental dichotomy with each other
but the strategies to fulfill that might
be in fundamental dichotomy so we come
to what is fundamentally meaningful and
ultimately what we end up finding is
that the same things are meaningful to
everyone that's not obvious at all but
everything that is actually meaningful
when you strip the strategy away is
meaningful to everyone now that that's a
process of Revelation that we actually
all have the same values which is all of
them right everything fundamentally
valuable then we get to say how do we do
an integrated design strategy it meets
both of these things simultaneously and
takes them out of being seen as
paradoxical right out of being seen as
fundamentally dichotomous because we can
meet them both simultaneously
I'm so happy you're in this world they
mail and - so how far is this initiative
and is there gonna be tools or is there
gonna be a process that will help people
to do the sense-making and and and you
plan to release that process or is there
a certain technology certain tool that
would help to do that and in the in the
beginning I think I heard you say
sensors but that I don't know if it's
applies to sense-making or to actual
sensors yes there I was saying human
sensors meaning that we're not in this
particular process we're looking at
humans as things that have sensed into
the world around them and can then share
their sense making and then there's a
way of being able to synthesize very
harvesting something as opposed to sense
making from say data mining on the
internet or physical sensors which are
also important and where you know they
those all need combined when we start to
talk about the future of infrastructure
physical sensors are actually a major
part of a self adapting system the
system I was just sharing of kind of
small group sense making process has
gone through architecture which is
actually very non-trivial as you're
hearing it's not it's not like a small
adaptation of holacracy or so she offers
here some other thing it was starting by
reverse engineering from the actual
social dynamic means and there's a
there's several different processes that
was one of them and just started to go
into prototyping and now there's a lot
of prototype work to do and I would
actually love to have people from the
you know collective intelligence
communities especially if they were
interested in helping to develop these
things further to do so because you know
a lot of work is needed yeah thank you
you
just as you were saying that I was
thinking about how to then enhance the
capacity of the sensors right and how do
you do that when you enter in collecting
intelligence because we can operate here
and we can interview our fears or we can
enter through our emotion or we can
enter that we can bring our whole selves
and that's literally all the good and
the bad and the ugly and the beautiful
and and so when you prepare a collective
field like if you think about the we
spaces preview part of who over the
practices are developing collective
sentence I'm developing a way on on how
we connect to each other so deeply but
also to the center to do that which is
bigger than ourselves
and then through that when we have
reached a certain space where where were
literally buzzing it would literally
feel the space is impregnated with our
beingness together with our easiness in
that particular moment of the collective
and then we go to the mind then more
powerful things can happen and I feel
that bad when you mix that and
experience when you mix that with music
let's say that in a certain point the
group reach the limit of their sensing
and then you bring an important piece of
music or art or so that that you know
meant the possibilities of the right
brain and left brain interaction in the
space and the body so I would say that
it would have to be larger than the mind
it would have to involve all of who we
are so that our sense source are really
fully activated and that would be my
answer I think that is beautiful and
desirable and not necessary for everyone
to start you're describing a kind of all
level all line all quadrants inner being
right synchrony some people live in
fairly narrows parts of their own being
in terms of what types of intelligences
they use and so if there's someone who
is living in a
really cognitive digital space without a
whole lot of somatic awareness they can
still get cognitively that there is no
way for Windows game theory to work and
the interconnectivity and the
interdependence of everything and they
can to the degree that that is actually
a basis of choice making for them they
can start making choices aligned with
that and they can develop those other
types of intelligence I say this because
I find that some groups that I connect
with should all do ayahuasca together
and then all dance together and have a
sniper party and like it connect them
that way and then they do strategy and
there are other groups of autists who
actually do really good strategy
together just by starting with data and
so I want to make it as deep and rich as
possible and as widely appealing as
possible thank you that addresses that
we are unique and that there is these
places for uniqueness and then the
places where certain groups I think that
that you know one of the recordings that
that I did on fury of the embodied we
with Erik Hersman or our God and they
were speaking about certain practices
like game shifting to make some words
that create collective awareness of
where we are at so it's like that
immediate sense making while we are in
process to know if we have bypassed
something that that we actually wanted
to agree upon in the in the moment how
help us keep our agreements in the field
help us know where we're at in regards
to a process in any given moment jumping
from example from a facilitated fully
facilitated group to oh now we're girl
facilitating or now we're popcorn doing
popcorn oh now we need to to dive deeper
into ourselves and connect vertically
and we want to soar so let's take a
brief before breath before we speak and
let's try to make the conversation
slower and that but then you can
dynamically do that
right so it's like in in a way
you could have you know boards that
could that could show that that could
indicate where the collective is at in
any given moment and individual words
that could indicate where you are at in
any individual moment yes and it's
tricky because when we think about
complex when we think about complex
adaptive systems and the kind of mmm
merging changing flowing dynamics that
can occur right if we look at at bees
and termites and ants and flocks and
schools like you mentioned earlier they
don't have prefrontal cortices and in
the stigma jeddak dynamics that do hive
intelligence that can be that adaptive
all of the members of the hive are
fungible to each other right they there
is no uniqueness of activity or role
based on the individual they all can do
exactly the same thing so they which is
why sting or G works as a signaling
system because they'll all do the same
thing to the same signal it's also why
they're fairly expendable as part of the
strategy of the hive but it's also why
they can count on each other to they can
pretty much know what the one intern of
them is going to do now when we come
into a situation and people have very
different learning styles and they have
different skills and different
attributes and so much so that we're
into full kind of uniqueness of self
then I can't assume that these six
people are going to operate at all the
same as the last six that I had which is
why command and control hierarchy has
worked so else is just all that
complexity let's make a complicated
system that we can rule and let's make
people fungible let's make sure that
everyone who's had an MBA can do these
things and everyone who's on the
assembly line can do these things but of
course that system is end-of-life right
and and running out so one of the things
I would say is that as we move in the
systems where we have to have more
complex and inner dynamical you know
relationships we've got to learn to
listen so much better and to communicate
so much better and to be able to
actually adapt to different processes
and different people which requires real
authentic full communication and so this
is where you're saying what is the what
is the development at the level of
individuals needed to make those kinds
of processes effective a lot Wow I'm
gonna rap because we've been going on
and of course we can keep going on and
it's just so beautiful but I want a name
into that last piece just said on this
make it really presence that we need to
be listening better that we need to be
then developing our sensing capacities
and our scent source and our way to
receive signals so that we can become
better players over that we space of
that collective and that is a beautiful
challenge for each one of us and a very
possible one is actually a very fun one
if you ask me thank you
so anything last question something that
I haven't asked that you want to to
share or any last sharing that you would
want to express very fun to be in this
conversation with you really a delight
and I appreciate it
Thank You Daniel me as well I appreciate
talking with you and just seeing you
light up with your bright bright genius
and presence and thank you for all the
work that you're doing likewise thank
you
[Music]
thank you for joining us on this
collective journeys to central more
speakers from the global we space summit
2 min to triple w the wisp a sunny calm
here you will find over 150 trailblazing
pioneers and we face experts as well as
26 catalysts convening these
conversations at the next stage of
collective consciousness and culture
[Music]